Guide to the Social Ethics Pamphlet Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Corporate Bodies, Series I
  - A
    - Americans for Democratic Action, 1947-1959 (Box 42, Folder 2-7)
      Subjects: United States--politics and government; Connecticut--politics and government; International relations
      Comments: contains papers from the non-partison liberal political action group including; materials from organizing convention, letters about national activities and materials issued by youth wing of the movement (Students for Democratic Action)
    - Americans for Traditional Liberties, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Comments: Contains draft of "An open letter to the American people" (to be released on Sept. 25, 1955, the 166th anniversary of the birth of the Bill of Rights).
    - Anti-Defamation League of B'Nai Brith (1 of 2), 1942-1963 (Box 42, Folder 8,9)
      Subjects: Antisemitism; Race relations
      Comments: contains pamphlets issued by the league on antisemitism and discrimination; newsletter Christian Friends Bulletin
    - Anti-Defamation League of B'Nai Brith (2 of 2) (Box 108)
    - Appreciate America, Inc., [1944-1945] (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Comments: Contains cartoon, flyer, two pamphlets.
    - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Geographical location: Aspen, CO
      Subjects: Education
      Comments: Contains "American higher education in 1980--Some basic issues," by John W. Nason (1965).
    - Association for Human Fellowship, Inc., 1945 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Subjects: Jews; Race relations
      Comments: Contains single issue of "Newsletter of the Association for Human Fellowship, Inc." devoted to one-volume encyclopedia entitled "The Jews" (1945).
    - Association for an International Protestant Radio Station, [1966] (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Geographical location: Lausanne, Switzerland
      Subjects: Broadcasting.
      Name changes etc.: Association Emetteur Protestant International (EPI); Verein Internationaler Evangelischer Radiosender
      Comments: Contains "Report of the working committee" on establishing an international Protestant radio station in Switzerland [1966].
    - Association of American Universities, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Subjects: Civil rights; Education; Academic freedom
      Comments: Contains "The rights and responsibilities of universities and their faculties" (1953).
    - Association of Catholic Conscientious Objectors, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Subjects: Peace movements; World War, 1939-1945; Catholic Church; Conscientious objectors.
      Comments: Contains single issue of "The Catholic C.O." (1946).
    - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, 1941-1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Subjects: Labor movement; Catholic Church
      Comments: The Association seeks "to foster and spread in the American labor movement sound trade unionism based on Christian principles." Contains two pamphlets on the history and purpose of the Association (1941), and "The Labor Leader" (1951).
    - Association of Citizens' Councils, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Geographical location: Greenwood, MS
      Comments: Contains two pamphlets attacking racial desegregation of public schools.
    - Association of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Comments: Pamphlet: "Postwar Agricultural Policy"
    - Association of Medical Students, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Comments: Contains report on birth control education in American medical schools.
    - Association of Methodist Ministers and Laymen, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Geographical location: Montgomery, AL
      Subjects: Race relations; Methodist Church--United States.
      Comments: Contains pamphlet maintaining the commitment of Alabama Methodist ministers and laymen to continued segregation of churches, schools, conferences, and jurisdictions on the basis of race.
    - Augustana Evangelical Lutheran Church, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Subjects: Birth control; Lutheran Church--United States
      Comments: Contains resolution on "Responsible parenthood" (1954).
    - Automotive Council for War Production, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      Geographical location: [Detroit, MI]
      Subjects: Labor movement; World War, 1939-1945
      Comments: Contains pamphlet "The manpower problem--What it really is," a presentation before the Senate War Investigating Committee (1945).
  - B
    - B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundations, 1945-1963 (Box 5, Folder 30)
      Geographical location: Washington, D.C.
      Subjects: Jews; Education; Church work with students
      Comments: Pamphlets, newsletters re. work among Jewish students on college and university campuses
    - Baha'i Publishing Trust, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      Geographical location: Wilmette, IL
      Subjects: Bahais; Race relations
      Comments: Contains pamphlet "Man one family," a summary of Baha'i attitudes towards Race relations
    - Baltimore Urban League, 1941-[1947] (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Geographical location: Baltimore, MD
      Comments: The League was organized to address the social and economic situation of the Black population in the city.File contains annual reports for 1941, 1943, 1945; publicity brochure [1947].
    - Baptist Joint Committee on Public Affairs, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      Subjects: Baptists; International relations;Civil rights
      Comments: Contains four issues of "Report from the Capital" newsletter (1951).
    - Barradas League (Box 5, Folder 23)
      Geographical location: San Francisco, CA
      Subjects: Economic policy; Labor movement; Capitalism.
      Comments: The League, founded in 1932, was named after Gerald Barrada, author of "Scientific Capitalism--Why and How" (1932). It purpose is to help "in the practical realization of Scientific Capitalism in America." Since 1936, through its educational program, "the League has periodically published releases containing comment on economic, political and ideological questions of public interest." Contains press releases on capitalism, labor, world government, Communism, Socialism, conservatism (1946-58); "The forgotten ideals of capitalism."
    - Berea College, [n.d.] (Box 5, Folder 24)
      Geographical location: Berea, KY
      Subjects: Race relations; Education
      Comments: Contains typescript adapted from "The Berea Alumnus" entitled "Each age must judge," which describes Berea's commitment to interracial education and advocates repeal of Kentucky's 1904 "Day Law" that outlawed the practice.
    - Bethlehem Community Center, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      Subjects: Alcoholism; Youth.
      Comments: Contains single issue of "Out of Bethlehem" (1944) devoted to "Drinking and delinquency."
    - Biosophical Institute, [194?]-1952 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      Subjects: Peace movements; Personality development.
      Comments: Through an extensive study of philosophy, religion, ethics, science, art, economics and politics, Dr. Frederick Kettner became interested in the problems of character development and peace Education; This new science, Dr. Kenner called 'Biosophy' (Bios--Life and Sophia--Intelligence).
    - Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      Comments: Contains "Medical, social, economic and religious aspects of birth control," by Sophia J. Kleegman (1938).
    - Birth Control Federation of America, 1940-1943 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      Comments: Contains five pamphlets, one typescript, one poster, and one chart on Birth control
    - Blue Cross of Philadelphia, [1946] (Box 5, Folder 29)
      Comments: Contains "Hospitalization" [1946], a pamphlet that discusses payment for health care in Philadelphia area hospitals.
    - Board of Aldermen (see New Haven, City of--Board of Aldermen), 1939-1945 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Subjects: Education--Afric. Education--Great Britain; Great Britain--Colonies; Labor movement--Great Britain
      Comments: Contains six pamphlets on subjects listed above.
    - British Information Services, 1939-1945 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Subjects: Education--Africa; Education--Great Britain; Great Britain--Colonies; Labor movement--Great Britain
    - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, 1943-1964 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Geographical location: Cleveland, OH
      Subjects: Labor movement; Arbitration and award.
      Comments: Contains biographical sketch of A. F. Whitney; "Religion, labor and the common good"; critical report on the 80th Congress; and memorandum about the 1962-63 negotiations between the union and railroads that resulted in Congress passing a compulsory arbitration law.
    - Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Comments: Contains "The Negro in American democracy," by A. Philip Randolph (1942).
    - Bulgarian Political Mission to the United States, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Subjects: International relations; Bulgaria--Politics and government.
      Comments: Contains "The truth about Bulgaria" (1946).
    - Bureau for Intercultural Education, 1941-1948 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Name changes etc.: Service Bureau for Intercultural Education
      Comments: The Bureau's purpose is to foster intercultural understanding to improve "democratic human relations through the schools" and to combat "tensions among Americans of varied religions, races, and nationalities, and the aggravation of problems brought about by social and economic conditions." Contains a report to the board (1946); two lists of publications on intercultural education; brochure about the bureau; several issues of "Intercultural Education News", and "Report on the Intercultural Education Workshop and the Bureau for Intercultural Education," by Harold C. Letts [n.d.].
    - Bureau of Business Practice, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Geographical location: New London, CT
      Comments: Contains "The human side: scrap the iron curtain" (1950).
    - Bureau of Educational Services (see Byron G. Moon Company--Bureau of Educational Services)
    - Bureau of Research and Planning (see Church Federation of Greater Chicago--Bureau of Research and Planning)
    - Bureau on Jewish Employment Problems, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Comments: Contains annual report "Manpower and minorities" (1943).
    - Byron G. Moon Company--Bureau of Educational Services, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Subjects: Economic policy; Agriculture; Automobile industry and trade; Petroleum industry and trade.
      Comments: Contains six pamphlets from the series "Evolution of our national & family income" on agriculture, motor vehicles, and the petroleum industry.
  - C
    - CARE, 1946-1949 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Subjects: World War, 1939-1945--Refugees; International relief.
      Name changes etc.: Cooperative for American Remittances to Europe
      Comments: Contains solicitation letter, two publicity brochures.
    - CORE (Congress of Racial Equality), [1942]-1960 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      Name changes etc.: Committee of Racial Equality; Congress of Racial Equality
      Comments: Contains several pamphlets, one newsletter, five flyers, one typescript on racial integration of restaurants and public schools, sit-ins, and passive resistance.
    - Campaign for World Government, Inc., 1954 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Geographical location: Brewster, NY
      Subjects: International relations; International organization.
      Comments: Re. movement for world government, including "Wanted: Christian pioneers," by Tracy D. Mygatt (1954).
    - Camps Farthest Out, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Subjects: Christian Education
      Name changes etc.: Silver Bay Association
      Comments: This interdenominational Protestant fellowship operates a camp in Silver Bay, NY, that offers lectures, discussions, prayers, creative arts, and meditation. "[They send] people back to their homes more effective Christians, who support the work of their churches and give spiritual strength to their communities." Contains solicitation letter, two pamphlets about the organization.
    - Canadian Association for Adult Education (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Geographical location: Toronto, ON (Canada)
      Subjects: Education--Canada; Labor movement--Canada; Mental health--Canada.
      Comments: Contains four pamphlets on above-mentioned subjects.
    - Canadian Conference of Christians and Jews, 1944-1945 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Subjects: Jews; Antisemitism--Canada; Christianity--relations--Judaism; Immigrants; Race relations--Canada.
      Comments: Contains eight issues of "Fellowship: the monthly bulletin of...Christians and Jews" (1944-45).
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1957-1964 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Comments: The Corporation, "a philanthropic foundation created by Andrew Carnegie in 1911 for the advancement and diffusion of knowledge and understanding," has "a continuing interest in improving higher Education;" Contains nine issues of the "Quarterly Report" (1957-64) covering such subjects as diversification in higher education, Africa, educational excellence, the international role of American universities, reading, public servants, and gifted students.
    - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Comments: Contains list of documents published in 1947, draft of a convention on international control of atomic energy and a pamphlet on the World Health Organization (WHO)
    - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Comments: Contains "The flight from teaching" (1964).
    - Carolina Israelite, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      Geographical location: Charlotte, NC
      Subjects: Jews
      Comments: Contains single issue of newspaper: "The Carolina Israelite" (1958).
    - Carrie Chapman Catt Memorial Fund, 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      Subjects: Civil rights; Citizenship.
      Comments: The Carrie Chapman Catt Memorial Fund is "a research and educational fund created by the League of Women Voters of the United States." Contains three pamphlets on American citizenship.
    - Carver Foundation of Norwalk, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      Geographical location: Norwalk, CT
      Subjects: Race relations; Community organization
      Comments: Leaflet describing purposes of the Foundation: "to advance public sentiment in favor of and to help make available adequate housing for the colored people of Norwalk and environs; to provide proper social and recreational facilities for their advancement and general welfare", etc.
    - Catechetical Guild Educational Society, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      Geographical location: St. Paul, MN
      Subjects: Communism; Subversive activities.
      Comments: Contains comic book "Is this tomorrow? America under Communism" (1947).
    - Catholic Action Students, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      Subjects: Education; Catholic Church; Race relations
      Comments: Two issues of "Leader's Bulletin"
    - Catholic Association for International Peace (Box 6, Folder 21)
      Subjects: Catholic Church; Hunger; Peace movements
      Comments: Contains five pamphlets on international peace and world hunger; "Statement on the U.N. draft covenant on human rights."
    - Catholic Information Society, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      Subjects: Catholic Church; Communism
      Comments: Contains 17 anti-Communist pamphlets on various subjects.
    - Catholic Interracial Council, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      Subjects: Catholic Church; Race relations
      Comments: Contains single issue of "International Review" (1960).
    - Catholic Pacifists' Association (Canada), 1944 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      Geographical location: Montreal, QE (Canada)
      Subjects: Catholic Church--Canada; Peace movements--Canada; World War, 1939-1945
      Comments: Contains "Blessed are the peacemakers" (1944), a sectarian historical overview of Catholic pacifism.
    - Catholic Truth Society of Oregon, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Geographical location: Portland, OR
      Subjects: Catholic Church--apologetic works.
      Comments: Contains "Catholic religion proved by Protestant Bible" (1956).
    - Catholic Worker Press, 1941-1943 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Subjects: Catholic Church; Labor movement
      Comments: Contains three pamphlets relating to the Catholic labor union movement.
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, 1961-1968 (Box 43, Folder 1-3b)
      Geographical location: Santa Barbara, CA
      Subjects: Broadcasting; Economic policy; Race relations; United States--politics and government
      Name changes etc.: Formerly known as the Fund for the Republic
      Comments: contains pamphlets with essays by notable figures on various issues in American society
    - Central Board for Conscientious Objectors, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Geographical location: London, England
      Subjects: Conscientious objectors--Great Britain.
      Comments: Contains single issue of "The Objector" (1950).
    - Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors, [1950] (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Subjects: Conscientious objectors.
      Comments: Contains "Amnesty for conscientious objectors" [1950].
    - Central Conference of American Rabbis, 1941-1948 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Geographical location: St. Louis, MO
      Subjects: Jews; Civil rights; Labor movement; Peace movements; Race relations
      Comments: Contains ten pamphlets on above-mentioned subjects; "Proceedings of the Institute on Justice and Peace" (1947).
    - Chamber of Commerce of the United States, 1946-1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Comments: Contains "Communist infiltration in the United States"; single issue of "Labor Relations Letter"; "The moral issue of 'right to work'."
    - Chaplain Counselors for Industry, Inc. (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Geographical location: Newark, NJ
      Subjects: Labor movement; Chaplains, Industrial.
      Name changes etc.: America's Inland Mission for Industrial Workers
      Comments: This organization offers to industry "Chapalin [sic] Counselors as specialists equipped with a working knowledge of important segments of the industrial field, with counseling skills in the use of...Theopsychotherapy and with other skills to dissolve some of the causes of industrial unrest." Contains "Information for industrial chaplain candidates."
    - Chicago Committee to Defend Democratic Rights, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Subjects: Civil rights; Subversive activities.
      Comments: Contains "We dissent: Supreme Court Justice Hugo Black's ringing declaration of his faith in freedom" (1959).
    - Chicago Council Against Racial and Religious Discrimination, [1943]-1950 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Comments: Contains 18 issues of "Against Discrimination" (1948-50); "Documented memorandum VIII" [n.d.]; "Report and recommendation for action on overcrowding in South Side schools" [n.d.].
    - Christ's Mission, Inc., 1948 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      Subjects: Catholic Church--controversial literature.
      Comments: Anti-Catholic; contains single issue of "The Converted Catholic Magazine" (1948).
    - Christian Action, 1951-1955 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Comments: Christian Action is a nationwide, voluntary association of churchmen, formed in 1951, "to seek a consensus of opinion on how church members could so participate in politics to the end of seeking a constructive policy for the nation." Contains first draft of constitution and by-laws (1954); report of the Executive Council (1954); single issue of "Religion at the News Desk" (1951) on the formation of Christian Action; "Statement on the Formosan situation" [1954]; "Statement on the proposed censure of Senator McCarthy" [1954]; "Draft policy statement on the People's Republic of China and the United Nations" (1955); "Foreign policy action sheet No. 4: The U.S. and world trade" (1955).
    - Christian Amendment Movement, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Geographical location: Topeka, KS
      Subjects: Social legislation; Religion and politics
      Comments: The Movement sought unsuccessfully to have the President and Congress "conserve our present Democratic Freedoms, safeguard them against further materialistic encroachments and undergird our nation for Christian leadership...by making in our Federal Constitution, a definite acknowledgment of the Authority and Law of Jesus Christ the Saviour and King of nations." Contains two pamphlets, two flyers, and one typescript describing the aims of the Movement.
    - Christian Commission for Camp and Defense Communities, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      Subjects: World War, 1939-1945; Community organization
      Comments: Commission was formed to coordinate programs for men and families displaced and moved around because of the war effort.
    - Christian Conference on War and Peace, 1943-1946 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      Subjects: International relations; Peace movements; World War, 1939-1945
      Name changes etc.: Administered by the World Alliance for International Friendship through the Churches.
      Comments: Purpose of group is "to help develop concerted action by those in the churches who recognize the unity of the war and the peace and the need to establish the nucleus of an effective world government". Includes "Survey of attitudes of U.S. senators on international issues", various newletters and statements.
    - Christian Council on Palestine, 1943-1946 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      Subjects: Jews; Israel-Arab conflicts; Christianity--Relations--Judaism; Palestine
      Comments: Includes eight pamphlets supporting Jewish claims to Palestine
    - Christian Faith and Life Community, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      Geographical location: Austin, TX
      Subjects: Christian communities; Church work with students.
      Comments: Newsletters of a Christian community located near the university in Austin.
    - Christian Freedom Foundation, 1950-1954 (Box 106)
      Subjects: Conservatism--conservative literature; Economic policy; Religion and culture
      Comments: contains extended collection of "Christian Economics" a conservative economic newspaper
    - Christian Peace Conference, 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      Geographical location: Prague, Czechoslovakia
      Subjects: Peace movements; Religion and politics
      Comments: Contains three issues of "Christian Peace Conference" (1970-72).
    - Christian Press (Box 7, Folder 17)
      Subjects: Catholic Church; Banks and banking.
      Comments: Contains pamphlet "Parish credit unions."
    - Christian Rural Fellowship, 1939-[1944] (Box 7, Folder 18)
      Subjects: Rural conditions; Missions--United States.
      Name changes etc.: International Association of Agricultural Missions
      Comments: The purpose of the Fellowship, founded in 1935, is "to promote Christian ideals for agriculture and rural life; to interpret the spiritual and religious values which inhere in the processes of agriculture and the relationships of rural life; to magnify and dignify the rural church; to provide a means of fellowship and cooperation among rural agencies: Toward a Christian Rural Civilization." Contains two issues of "The Christian Rural Fellowship Bulletin"; fact sheet about the Fellowship.
    - Christian Soldiers, Inc., 1947 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      Subjects: Armed Forces; Missions--United States.
      Comments: An inspirational mission
    - Church Federation of Greater Chicago--Bureau of Research and Planning, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      Comments: Contains "Study of parish lines for Park Forest"; "Outline of a constitution for united Protestant churches in Park Forest"; "Opportunity Negro"; "Opportunity Industrial."
    - Church League of America, [1940] (Box 7, Folder 22)
      Subjects: Civil rights; Freedom of religion
      Comments: Contains "An urgent appeal...to every churchman in America" [1940].
    - Church Peace Union and World Alliance for International Friendship Through Religion, 1931-1958 (Box 7, Folder 24)